Guide to the Emir Rodriguez Monegal Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Emir Rodriguez Monegal papers
1959-1985
MS 1750
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The papers consist of correspondence and subject files related to the professional life of Emir Rodriguez Monegal as an expert in Latin American literature and language.
Rodríguez Monegal, Emir, 1921-1985
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was transferred from Bryn Mawr, 1996.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research with the exception of the correspondence series, which is restricted until January 1, 2059.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, 1959-1983. II. Organizations, 1964-1985. III. Yale University, 1964-1985. IV. Subject Files, 1968-1985.
Biographical / Historical
Emir Rodriguez Monegal was born in Melo, Uruguay, in 1921. He was a member of the Yale University faculty from 1969 until his death in 1985. At various times Rodriguez Monegal served as chairman and director of graduate studies of the Department of Spanish and Portuguese. He was a visiting professor at several universities, including Harvard University, the University of Southern California, El Colegio de Mexico, Universidade Federal in Rio de Janeiro, and the University of Pittsburgh. Rodriguez Monegal was an expert on Latin American literature and the author of a literary biography of Jorge Luis Borges and several other books. He also served as editor of numerous literary magazines. He married Selma Calasans and had three children. Rodriguez Monegal died in New Haven on November 21, 1985.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence and subject files related to the professional life of Emir Rodriguez Monegal as an expert in Latin American literature and language.
Latin American literature; Portuguese language; Spanish language; Rodríguez Monegal, Emir, 1921-1985; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1959-1983; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains correspondence related to the professional life of Emir Rodriguez Monegal and is arranged in alphabetical order by last name of correspondent.
  Conditions Governing Access
  These records are restricted until January 1, 2059.
  - Brombert, Victor, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Corbatta, Jorgelina, 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correa, Gustavo, 1959, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - De Campos, Harold, 1977-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - de la Torre, Jose Ramon, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Echevarria, Roberto, 1975-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Goldsen, Joseph, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gyurko, Lanin, 1972-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - MacAdam, Alfred, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Maingot, Anthony, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Muller-Bergh, Klaus, 1971-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Orthman, Nora Gladys, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Piedra, Jose, 1980, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Resnick, Margery, 1973-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 14 - 15)
  - Santi, Enrico, 1973-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Schwartz, Jorge, 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Taft, Horace [re: fraudulent memo], 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Organizations, 1964-1985, Series II
  The series contains correspondence and other materials related to the professional organizations with which Rodriguez Monegal was affiliated, and is arranged in alphabetical order by name of organization.
  - Colegio de Mexico, 1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Cuba/Haiti Research Project, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Latin American Political Guide, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Library of Congress, 1975-1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Moore Fund, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Wilson Center, 1982-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Yale University Files, 1964-1985, Series III
  The series contains materials related to faculty committees with which Rodriguez Monegal worked and other aspects of his professional life at Yale University, and is arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
  - Administration and Committees, 1973- 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Literature Studies, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Concilium grants, 1969- 1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Concilium on International and Area Studies, 1970 -1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Council on Latin American Studies, 1975- 1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Council on Modern Studies, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Department of Comparative Literature, 1972- 1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Department of Spanish, 1969-1977, 1980, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Griswold Fund, 1973, 1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Leaves of absence, 1970, 1975-1980, 1983, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Library [Latin American Collection], 1970, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Teaching [class on avant-garde], 1978, 1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Term appointments report, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Yale-Mellon Program, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, 1968- 1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 15 - 16)
- Subject Files, 1968-1985, Series IV
  The series contains materials related to the professional life of Emir Rodriguez Monegal, and is arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
  - Columbia University, 1975-1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum vitae, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Personal finances and retirement benefits, 1972- 1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Publications, 1970-1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Speaking engagements, 1968-1969, 1977-1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - University of Pittsburgh, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - University of Southern California, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970, 1975, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)